ACTWU's Local 169 Records 5619/014
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ACTWU's Local 169 Records
1923-2003
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America. Local 169 (New York, N.Y.)
Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union. Local 169 (New York, N.Y.)
5619/014
4 cubic feet
4 linear feet
Correspondence, reports, publications.
This collection consists of collective bargaining agreements, convention proceedings, meeting minutes, publications, and files from the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, Local 169, and the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union, Local 169.
6766550
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
March 08, 2010
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, July 2010
Biographical / Historical
The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, the most significant union representing workers in the men's clothing industry, was founded in New York City in 1914 as a breakaway movement from the United Garment Workers. Radical and immigrant workers in the tailors' and cutters' locals were the core of the seceding group, which advocated industrial unionism and economic strikes in opposition to the UGW's craft organization, which they saw as conservative and timid. Their diverging views had come to the fore during the historic 1910 dispute at the Chicago firm Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. The opposition called the strike against the UGW leadership's advice, and reached a path-breaking agreement with management that established an arbitration system to settle disputes.
Members flocked to the new union. Around 50,000 strong at its founding, by 1920 the ACWA counted about 170,000 members. Initially composed mostly of immigrants of Jewish European descent with Socialist leanings, the ACWA quickly welcomed members of a great number of nationalities and diverse backgrounds. Like in other garment unions, most workers and many members were women, but the leadership was predominantly male, a situation that did not change for many decades. Early on the union adopted a centralized administrative structure combined with industrial unionism, with the joint boards' by-laws having precedence over those of locals.
Espousing a philosophy perhaps brought over by its early immigrant socialist members, the Amalgamated went beyond bread and butter issues and adopted a distinctive form of social unionism that was largely absent in the American labor movement. Starting in the 1920s, it provided educational opportunities and recreational facilities for its members, as well as services such as an insurance plan, banks offering personal loans at low interest rates, low-cost housing cooperatives, medical clinics, and even union-owned restaurants.
Sidney Hillman was the first president of the new union and the most important officer in its history. He applied his experience as bargaining representative in Chicago to the whole industry. Under his leadership the union made significant strides in securing better wages and working conditions for its members, and at the same time it consolidated gains and provided stability to the industry through the widespread adoption of the arbitration system tested at Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. Hillman paid close attention to industry issues, such as production, pricing, and marketing. In order to help management meet the competition of non-union firms, the union conducted studies of efficiency, work methods, and factory costs. Letters to the official publication of the union, Advance, document the controversy that ensued within the union over what was perceived to be collaboration with management.
Hillman also understood the importance of labor's involvement in national affairs and political action. In the 1920s the ACWA sent delegates to the Conference for Progressive Political Action and to the Farmer-labor party conventions. Although many members and officers were Socialists, the union stopped short of officially endorsing the party. Communist attempts at gaining influence within the union were firmly curbed. Hillman's participation in national affairs and politics became prominent during the New Deal, when he became a close advisor to Franklin D. Roosevelt on labor and economic issues. He also served on the board of the National Recovery Administration. Later, during World War II, he helped establish the Labor's Non Partisan League. He was also named associate director of the Office of Production Management, which assisted in mobilizing the nation's resources for the war effort. Hillman's prestige perhaps reflected the healthy condition of his union, which by the end of the conflict was strong and stable.
During the post World War II period the union faced a number of significant challenges. Membership continued to grow (peaking at 395,000 in 1968), but the union's political influence and visibility in national affairs declined. In their never ending pursuit of lower production costs, many firms relocated to the South, forcing the union to engage in large organizing efforts. Simultaneously, signs began to appear of changes that would lead to the almost complete demise of the domestic apparel industry and, ultimately, to the erosion of union membership. Foreign imports of cheap clothing goods steadily grew in the 1950s and 1960s, and mushroomed in the following two decades, plunging employment in the apparel sector into a steady decline. Union efforts to stem the tide included Buy American campaigns and extensive lobbying in Congress, but they were to no avail. In 1976, the ACWA merged with the Textile Workers of America to become the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. Despite successful and much publicized nationwide actions such as the Farah boycott and the J.P. Stevens corporate campaign, the woes threatening the union's existence continued unabated. The fate of the domestic industry was sealed in the late 1970s and the 1980s by the flight of firms chasing tax breaks and cheap labor abroad. By 1995, when ACTWU voted to merge with the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, their combined membership was 350,000. The new Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE!) seemed poised to infuse new life in a troubled union.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related collections: 5619: Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America All other 5619 collections, and 6000/016: UNITE's Local 169. Green & Grocery Campaign files
Collective bargaining--Clothing industry--New York (State); Clothing workers--Labor unions--New York (State); Clothing trade--New York (State); Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union --Archives; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union. Local 169 (New York, N.Y.) --Archives; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America --Archives; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America. Local 169 (New York, N.Y.)--Archives; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union --Archives; Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees --Archives; Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees. Local 169 (New York, N.Y.)--Archives; UNITE HERE (Organization) --Archives
6766550
- Agreement: A. Levine Incorporation - Ashland Uniform Company, 1939-1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Agreement: Bell Laundry - Buriable Pants Company, 1933-1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Agreement: C and L Overall Company - Dun Rite Laundry Company, 1937-1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Agreement: Edmund Muschel - Fur Fit Undergarment Incorporation, 1941-1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Agreement: General Sportwear Manufacturing Company - Hi Line Company Incorporated, 1941-1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Agreement: I. Schwartz and Son - Infant and Juvenile Manufacturers Association Incorporated, 1937-1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Agreement: J.H Harris Corporation - Juvenile Guild Incorporation, 1938-1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Agreement: Kaplan Janis Company - Lou Hy Sportswear Company, 1937-1946 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Agreement: M.E Greenfield Company - Mills Uniform Corporation0, 1937-1954 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Agreement: National Family Laundry Incorporation - Oxford Pants Company, 1937-1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Agreement: P. Lichtment and Son Company - Pyramid Knitwear Company Incorporated, 1937-1946 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Agreement: Queen Mary Togs Incorporated - Rubin Sportwear Incorporated, 1937-1947 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Agreement: S and I Novelty Company Incorporated - Stanley Togs, 1937-1946 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Agreement: Star Novelty Company Incorporated - Sweeney Block and Company Incorporated, 1940-1946 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Agreement: T and S Sportswear Company Incorporated - Tom Tinochiano, 1941-1947 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Agreement: Uniform Manufacturer's Exchange Incorporated - White Duck Management Company, 1937-1947 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Agreement: Youth Merit Wear Incorporated - Zone Novelty Company Incorporated, 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Mr. Bernstein - Miscellaneous, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous Union Documents, 1937-1950 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- ACWA Local 169, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Scope and Contents
  Mostly Photographs
- ACWA 23rd Biennial Convention, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Unsigned Agreements, 1937-1953 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Mr. Thomas Flavell (folder 1 of 2), 1969 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Financial information for appealing companies in the Sweater and Knit Swimwear industry in Puerto Rico
- Mr. Thomas Flavell (folder 2 of 2), 1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Puerto Rico: Additional statistical tables, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  April
- Miscellaneous, 1977-2003 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Minute Book, 1923-1926 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Language: Yiddish
- Local 169 A.C.W.A Minute Book, 1953-1965 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Executive Council Manual, 1953-1955 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Sick Benefit Minute Book, 1940-1950 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Minute Book, 1926-1932 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Executive Council Manual, 1947-1950 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Executive Council Recording Book, 1936-1941 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Proceedings: Nineteenth Biennial Convention, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Textile Workers of America
- Proceedings: Merger Convention, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers; Washington D.C
- The United States Department of Labor, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Author: James P. Mitchell (secretary)
- How do Labor and Schools work together?, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  National Citizens Council for Better Schools
- "this union cause", 1962 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  An illustrated history of Labor Unions in America
- Special Convention, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Convention Proceedings
- 50th Anniversary Convention, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  General Executive Board Report and Convention Proceedings; (2 copies)
- 20th Biennial Convention (General Executive Board Report and Proceeding), 1956 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  May 21-25
- Resolutions: 23rd Biennial Convention, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  May 14th
- 18th Biennial Convention, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  May 12-16; (4 copies)
- 20th Biennial Convention (General Executive Board Report), 1956 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  2 copies
- Correspondence, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Amalgamated Mimeo Handbook, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  Prepared by Barbara Wertheimer; Drawings by Frank Hanley
- Clippings and Memo of Local 169's Past History, 1942-1970 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Report of the General Executive Board: 2nd Constitutional Convention, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  June 1-5
- Textile Union Workers Union of America Volunteer Organizing Program, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- The Sweater and Knit Swimwear Industry in Puerto Rico, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  March
- Mr. Bernstein Certificate of Membership to the 66 club, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Immigration Law Material, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  Language: English and Spanish
- Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union Substance Abuse Manual, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Estado Libre Asociado de Puerto Rico, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  Oficina de Asuntos Laborales (OAL); Language: English and Spanish
- AFL-CIO Miscellaneous pamphlets, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- The Values We Cherish, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  Author: Walter P. Reuther
- Convention Proceedings: 1st Constitutional Convention, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  September 25-29
- Pamphlets on Health Care for Senior Citizens, 1943-1963 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- The Sidney Hillman Foundation Incorporated: Fifteen Year Report, 1948-1963 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Profile of a Union, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America
- Handbook for Industry Committee Members, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  United States Department of Labor
- Annual Awards Celebration, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health
- Retired and Remembered, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- The Story of a Bank: The Amalgamated Bank of New York, 1923-1963 (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Report of the General Executive Board: 1st Constitutional Convention, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 32)
- War Labor Board Decisions, 1944-1945 (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Executive Summary: The Antitrust Controversy, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  February
- Miscellaneous, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Blue Shield in New York City: a report and program, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  New York Labor-Management Council of Health and Welfare Plans, Incorporated
- Songbook Compilation of Rhythm and Music from all over the World, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  Compiler: Edith Berkowitz; Language: English and Spanish